Guide to the Rice University Hispanic History Project, 1924-2003 UA 311
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Hispanic History Project
1924-2003
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Hispanic Association for Cultural Enrichment at Rice (HACER)
UA 311
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Materials collected by the Hispanic Association for Cultural Enrichment at Rice (HACER)to document the history of Hispanics at Rice University, including written and oral accounts of alumni from the 1920s-1950s.
Biographical / Historical
Established in 1972, the Hispanic Association for Cultural Enrichment at Rice (HACER) is one of the most visible organizations for Hispanics on campus. HACER offers many opportunities for all members of the Rice community to enjoy such as cultural, educational, political, service, outreach, and social activities.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials collected by the history committee of the Hispanic Association for Cultural Enrichment at Rice (HACER) to document the history of Hispanics at Rice University.
Series I contains written biographical and autobiographical material of Hispanic alumni as well as photographs, newsclippings, memorabilia, rosters, and information on alumni activities in the early 2000s.
Series II contains information on events and activities of HACER and the Hispanic community of Greater Houston, including newsletters and publicity materials.
Series III contains primarily audio and video interviews of Hispanic alumni and their experiences at Rice during the 1920's-1950's.
Portions of this collection were received from Hispanic students of Rice from the 1940's and 1950's in response to a 2001 written invitation from HACER to write and/or tape record their experiences at Rice, while information from the 1920's and 1930's was largely obtained working with the Niño and Gonzales families.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred directly to the Fondren Library by HACER.
Index Terms
Subjects
Latin Americans; Hispanic Amercan college students; Universities and colleges
Document Types
audiotapes; photographs; videotapes
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Hispanic Alumni information files, 1924-2002, 156713
  - Caram, Dorothy Farrington, 1954-2001; 156716 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cavazos, Ninfa, 1992-1997; 156717 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cox, Mary Christine Niño, 2001-2003; 156718 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Flores, Mary Alice, 1924-1979; 156719 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gomez, Placido A., 1992; 156720 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sarabia, Emilio Albert, 1996, 2001, n.d.; 156721 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yramategui, Hector, 1981; 156722 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hispanic alumni and related materials, 2000-2002; 156723 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rice Homecoming and Society of Latino Alumni programs and video, November 15-17, 2002; 156726 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: Society of Latino Alumni of Rice, n.d.; 156724 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Rice and Houston Hispanic Communities, 2000-2002, 156714
  - HACER: Club activities and publications; 2000 Campanile group photo, 2000-2002, n.d.; 156725 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - HACER: Website, 2002; 156728 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - RICE-TMS Scholarship, 2001-02; 156729 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Institute of Hispanic Culture of Houston, 2002; 156727 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III: Audio-Visual Materials, 1979; 2000-2002, 156715
  - Subseries A: Interviews on audiocassette, 1979; 2000-01; 156730
    - Caram, Dorothy Farrington; 2 cassettes, sides 1-4 (2 copies), April 9, 2001; 156858 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cavazos, Ninfa; 2 cassettes, sides 1-4 (2 copies), April 9, 2001; 156859 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Flores, Mary Alice - Rice '55; 2 cassettes, March 2001; 156861 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Gonzales, Edmundo R.; 2 cassettes, sides 1-4 (2 copies), October 20, 2000; 156862 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Niño, Primitivo interviewed by Tom Kreneck; 1 cassette, March 16, 1979; 156863 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Note:
      45 minutes of excerpts from original of Houston Metropolitan Research Center
  - Subseries B: Video, 2000; 2002; 156731
    - Hacer Presentation; Edmundo Gonzales Interview (VHS), October 19, 2000; October 20, 2000; 156857 (Box 2, Folder -)
    - Rice University Homecoming Weekend: SOLAR's RAMAS 30th Anniversary Celebration (VHS), November 15, 2002; 156860 (Box 2, Folder -)
- Series IV: Oversize Materials, 160675
  - Panoramic B&W photograph of the 1951 graduate class of Milby High School, Houston, TX (Mary Alice Flores), 160676 (Map-drawer 148, Item 6)
    General Note
    Rice University Architectural drawings, oversize manuscript material, maps and photographs, Part 3 of 3 (UA 226-3)